the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right enough of that sexy music so
welcome
everyone to the stoa i'm peter limberg
the steward of the stoa
still was a place for us to cohere and
dialogue about what matters most
at the knife's edge of this very moment
and today we have
christian sawyer with us um christian is
um
one of the fellow meta tribal weirdos at
the stoa uh
is very intelligent guy and we've been
having a lot of exchanges
about uh psycho technologies
and how to arrange them
and sort of take ownership and
a sense of agency around our
relationship
to psychotechnologies and i suggested
the term uh
bespoke psychotechnology which he wasn't
a really big fan of but my jazzy
proclivity for titles
one out and that one so
agree on you okay yeah and so it's not
the idea it's not only the idea of kind
of rearranging like having a psycho
uh psycho technology stack um like you
know meditation followed by breath work
or whatever but also a way to be
take little parts of it and create your
own um so maybe this is a meta
psychotechnology that we can uh
eventually have at the stoa
and so this is going to be a starting
conversation of that
so christian is going to it's gonna be a
very interactive session uh he'll he'll
give the
agenda in a moment uh so i'll hand it
over to him it's 90 minutes
afterwards she'll take me in at the end
to do some closing announcements
but that being said i think that is
everything um
there's components so we're gonna record
the whole thing and i don't really know
how active their participation is so but
if you feel uncomfortable
uh don't feel shy to participate if you
feel comfortable being recorded
just let me know uh before or after and
i'll make sure that
portion won't be put on youtube so that
being said uh
christian i will take you in
oop i just uh unmuted everyone and then
uh or allowed everyone to meet
themselves which
i muted you so yeah got it um yeah
happy to be here excited to talk about
something i've been thinking about for a
long time
uh as i was getting closer as we're all
getting closer to being here
i was thinking about collective
presencing
and how much i love
the way that that psychotechnology
creates a group
feel so i was thinking about adding a
little bit of that into this session
um so what i'm going to do is i'm going
to first give like a brief
overview of like what i plan on talking
about
and then we're going to take a couple
minutes to just sink in and be present
we're not gonna do like a round of
sharing or anything like that
uh but if something does feel alive for
you you could put it in the chat
um and also it could be a time to think
of any questions
you have anything that that just kind of
comes to mind about the
the ideas i'm going to give the brief
overview of
and then we could start if any questions
come up we could kind of use that as a
starting place to generate a
conversation
i had a whole like you know
almost an hour worth of stuff to talk
about but i i was thinking it'd be nicer
to start
at the group level and let that guide
everything
uh but if no questions come up i'll just
kind of dive right in
so the basic idea of
bespoke psycho technology my
my runners-up terms were psychotech
stacking which peter explained was
not cool and i agree and then there was
also modular psychotech which i think
appeals to me as a musician
and a kind of a nerdy title
but whatever you want to call it the
basic idea is to
understand psycho technologies
um in a way that um
you can break them down and know how
they work rather than just see them as
this solid
you know uh instruction book given to
you from
uh someone some tradition some teacher
whatever uh and the reason the
well the reason i have found that to be
so helpful is because
i've had a lot of troubles trying to
practice different psycho technologies
meditation or working with psychedelics
um really anything even like collective
presencing or holotropic breath work
so the idea is to understand
all the constituent aspects of any
technology
so that then you can kind of get your
fingers in there and know how you might
change it alter it modify it and then to
understand
yourself um at a in a way that relates
to psychotechnology so you can kind of
know
where you might be bumping up against
difficulties with the psychotechnology
or know
what you want to get out of it that
you're not quite getting
um and that can one help you tweak the
tech and also
give you an idea of oh you know what
maybe this technology isn't
really what i need to be focusing on
right now
and understanding the kind of theory of
psychotech might help point you to a
different
technology or you might understand oh i
need to like kind of bring in
another psychotech that'll help to
regulate some aspect of my practice so
that it actually works the way i want to
work
so that's the brief overview and now
we're going to take
a couple minutes to settle down and
you can do whatever you want just be
silent maybe
uh register everybody's little face box
and and connect with the group or do a
little meditation
and if and like i said if any questions
are already coming up or do come up
during these two minutes feel free to
pop them in the
chat and uh i don't know if i'll
maybe i'll let peter uh feel
them and if yeah whatever feels good to
ask now
then we can talk or i'll just go into
the presentation so
it's 308 start around 3 10.
so do you want to field the questions
now or do you want to do the exercise
now
i'd like to uh just take the couple
minutes of silence first
right yeah
yeah i hope that was a nice
couple minutes to sink in and uh
yeah if there's any questions peter that
are already coming up
yeah so um sammy did you want to ask
your question
you cannot meet yourself hello
hey hey christian so my question was
i've been interested in all of these
practices for a long time
and they all resonate with me but at
this point
if you're talking about psychotechnology
what is the motivation to
have them grouped under one concept like
how does that serve us
to have an umbrella term
um well
i suppose the term specifically
psychotechnology i find helpful
because when you
if we were to use like the umbrella term
like meditation
that limits a lot of the
practices which might be useful to
combine with each other
so it could be really useful to combine
say something like qigong
or yoga or um
well just about just about anything that
you're doing with the
intention of affecting your own
psyche mixed in with something like
meditation or
prayer or like a group collective
practice
so the idea is to create like a space
where you can
see a bunch of different practices that
have like pretty meaningful interactions
with each other
does that make sense
yes yes and i think
that the mixing of practices people have
done it in their own ways
in you can see how yoga or meditation
has branched out
okay and that makes sense now yeah
yeah already have a an ecology of
practices so to speak
anything else peter
uh so uh christian
uh you get a question or statement and
so did nick if you guys can
christian first then nick
we can't hear you
nope um maybe um
we'll take a nick first and then while
you work on your audio issues christian
can i be heard yeah you can hear me yeah
hey there yeah
maybe you'll get into this as you as you
start to
um do your presentation but i was
i keep wondering because there's so many
you know floating around
and i don't know any of them that deeply
i suppose collective presencing the most
but i keep wondering are they all uh
like
sitting under something higher that's
like a meta
psycho technology or a series of really
basic
things that you could use in almost any
circumstance under almost any conditions
to tackle almost any kind of question
or is it more important not to think
like that and to be like no no you need
the right tool for the
you know if you've got a hammer
everything looks like a nail you need
the right tool for the right job
like that i know where's the level
between those two
yeah so
you're asking if
the idea is to create like such a
powerful psychotech
that it can be used for anything or to
have an idea of a
collection of psychotechs where you find
the appropriate tech for the appropriate
situation and desired outcome
are you asking like which am i trying to
talk about
uh i was more of a philosophical
question i was
asked earlier which is do you think that
there's something that sits above all
these psycho technologies this
like a fundamental thing or or or not
is it more like no no there's no need to
think about that yeah all you want to
think about is the individual pieces and
how they apply to different situations
well i think the two go hand in hand if
i'm understanding your correction
correctly and the first thing i'm going
to go into is what i'm going to call
embodied metaphysics and i wouldn't
say that you might unders you might say
it underlies
psychotech more than sits above but yeah
it'll be like a foundational
framework for how to understand
psychotechnology
understand yourself and so that way you
can know
how to like you know circuit board this
technology for this
yeah so yeah we'll go into that a bit
christian did you get your uh audio
figured out no sorry
uh you want to read it peter yeah read
on his behalf um
my sense is that psychotechnologies are
being promoted in a capitalistic society
as individual practice what is your
interest in having psychotechnologies
for groups
what are you selling us chris christian
yeah um well
um i like psycho technologies for groups
and i like for instance collective
presencing and
i am definitely interested in more of
that i'm not here to sell
anyone on that idea but i would be
thrilled if um the kind of concepts i'm
going over were to lead to the
development of more group
psychotechnology practices
um i do
in regard to like how psychotechs
meet with capitalism
uh i'd say
well i guess here's part of
why
i want to share this in the first place
which is
a lot of times psychotechnology is
presented
in the western world in the context of
you know
you're just generally trying to
self-improve or something like really
uh vague like i want more peace or um
i have too many inner thoughts or
something like that
and you just kind of have this like idea
of what it's supposed to get you
and then here's the practice with your
instructions and like
just you know follow the instructions so
you can get the the correct output right
and i would say that like going into the
uh the deeper philosophy of a psychotech
is to explore at least impart your
motivations for
doing it in the first place like what am
i really trying to get to like i say i
want like
more peace but what does that mean in an
embodied sense like
what's what exactly is going on within
me that doesn't feel peaceful
right um and when things are delivered
in a more like
capitalist way they're trying to sell
you on it and so you just kind of get
stuck i think sometimes with like the
goal
or maybe the tradition is selling you on
enlightenment or salvation
or healing or whatever
and so by like breaking things down a
bit i think it
it can be helpful to bring it home in
like a really deep and personal way
rather than trying to fit yourself into
a narrative of what the psychotech is
supposed to do
yeah i hope that answers that question a
bit and i'll add something to that
from kind of like the stewarding the
stoic perspective
um one thing first of all just comment
on the capitalistic co-opting
of psychotech like the whole kind of
mindfulness phenomenon where you take my
mindfulness meditation or meditation to
sort of you know make you be a more
productive worker or whatever
and then like the whole they co-op
stoicism too i call it serenity bucks
um or you know you take stored
principles to be better
that's more successful at things
cognitive behavioral therapy gets
criticism for this as well
um but i really like this idea of taking
ownership of the psychotechnology and in
creation creating it
because i think there's a default uh
expectation people have like oh where's
the perfect system just give it to me
and then you're not only just taking the
system or the practices but you're
taking the ideology that's attached to
it
by taking ownership of developing
practices you do what christian says
where you
examine your own motives and maybe the
ideologies that are attached to it
yeah very well put um
i think there's uh a lot to be there's a
lot of wisdom
in especially the older traditions
like for instance you brought up yoga um
uh i forget the name sami you know i
like how you know
the hindu traditions there's uh the yoga
traditions meditation
and different forms of meditation and
yoga ashram setting stuff like this it
all kind of came together and it's worth
considering
why they put all those things together
um
i think that would be the wise thing to
do but that doesn't mean you have to
take it all
as presented um yeah
okay so we have a bunch of we have two
other questions maybe three uh do you
wanna
feel them now or yeah i'd love to okay
so this is let's uh um let's go in order
um
him you got a question
okay yeah um thanks for this
christian and peter um
i just i mean the the term
psychotechnologies you know 10 years ago
we'd be going to what
and and yet as you said you know yoga
existed
has existed for a long time there's a
lot of things that have existed
but somehow it's feeling more and more
like
um like there's some movement in this
whole notion which is
why we actually come up with a frame
that's called psychotechnologies
that uh like together they're
into reaching together there's some kind
of
um interaction and so my question is
like do you see that that there's more
interactions between what we're now
calling psychotechnologies and
and i also would say there's more of
them
um and is there a sense
of them uh collectivizing or
forming um you know
moving in some new direction
collectively
without overreaching that that may be a
big question
uh but i kind of like that futuristic
thinking yeah
i mean it's it would be i
almost want to say it's like
self-evident that
the the rising popularity of psycho
technologies
is indica uh indicative of um
you know the path of humanity itself
and us like being together in different
ways
um and i do see a lot of already
of combining and mixing and matching and
uh
different psychotechnologies influencing
each other basically i think it's what
you said at the beginning there
um and i will when i'm
start going into some of my like
personal stories uh and experiences i
can speak to that
where i've discovered mixed up
psychotechnologies in the wild
but yeah i think and it's hard to know
sometimes too
like someone can just say like here's
the psychotech
and it seems like its own thing and you
have no idea like what influenced it
like what practices had
that person or that group of people
already been doing which led to the
emergence of some new psychotic right
so yeah i mean i think i can see
like known examples of it and i often
presume
and sometimes guess at you know the
roots of different psychotechnologies
how they were influenced by other psycho
technologies
yeah thank you for that question
i'll go into that more a bit too as we
get further along
all right uh evan you had a question
yeah
um sorry for the length so um my
my question is this so in some
traditions which have very rich veins of
psychotech to mind for example
vajrayana there's a sense which we've
mentioned here on the stowa on evolving
ground of there being both a method
and a view and without the matching view
the method may be useless or worse so
this can
create some difficulties with the idea
of remixing or repurposing psychotics
from these traditions without adequate
consideration for the compel
compatibility of their respective views
and i'm especially concerned about this
sort of thing in light of the sense that
traditions often have embedded within
them non-obvious wisdom which may not be
explicitly stated but which is implicit
to the way that practices are
traditionally transmitted
so say the ecosystem of psychotics
within vajrayana may be mutually
supportive one may serve as a bomb to
soothe the rawness left by another for
example and we could also mention slate
star codex or sarah constantine's
thoughts about the
implicit wisdom and tradition so this
also has implications for psychedelics
where the method may be something like
take psychedelics with good people in a
good setting but the view required to
actually manifest these positive
experiences consistently is much more
difficult to pen down
so people taking the method without
being inculcated in the view can have
frankly disastrous results so
i just wanted to hear your thoughts
about developing an intuition for which
psychotechs are
safe or effective when decontextualized
from the traditions in which they arose
and which ones can be more or less
lifted as independent modular units and
repurposed without so many issues as
well as anything else this question
brings up for you
thank you yeah wow that's a great
question
um and a really big one
i don't have a like uh i don't think
there is really like
a rule book on how to navigate that
issue
um but the kind of basic
principles i've had and you know part of
my my background in understanding this
is having
practices presented to me
decontextualized
and then going and researching and
finding proper context
um and that yeah makes can make all the
difference
so when it comes to like kind of getting
out there on your own and like trying to
mess around with stuff
which
i would say do it with a lot of caution
and this will be something i speak about
more but
you know there because things can get
hairy
and difficult um i'd say
part of one of the major principles in
in
messing around it's kind of like being a
hacker you know
um you don't want to just start
around with code because you can break
your laptop out and won't turn on again
you know so when it comes to any type of
of mixing and matching especially when
you're like
taking something decontextualized from
the tradition especially if it's a
somatic thing
psychedelics um real body oriented stuff
you're it it can be you can be touching
parts of yourself that you're not really
understanding very well and it can be
very powerful and it can have a
a momentum to it that you don't
necessarily know how to put the brakes
on
so it's really good to go slowly i think
especially when you're doing something
new where there's not a lot of wisdom
uh like contextual wisdom around the
practice
um and so what i'll be presenting is you
know
not like hey isn't it like cool to like
you know be a mad scientist
um with things but kind of like
understanding the the
philosophy of psychotechnology so you
can understand like when something
might need more context um or or the the
consequences of removing something from
this context
but also um knowing when the given
like view per se might not really jive
with you
um and like okay maybe i need to like
take this but
you know i want to take this view as
well
what's a wise way to do that so yeah
it's a whole
it's a whole complicated messy world and
uh we're just like i'm just like a
newbie
in it as much as anyone else except that
i've like
thought about it a lot over the last few
years and it's just because i've been
running into so much trouble
um and and yeah like messy messy stuff
can happen with psycho technology so
really good question um and i hope that
what i present here
is going to help people not you know get
into hairy situations rather than
lead them into you know the wild where
they're gonna get up
basically i have um
a thought for you christian um that
piggy backs off evan's
uh comment uh samuel berger has this
really
good term i like called the intellectual
dark matter so it's like all the kind of
intellectual architecture
that is not explicitly known by people
who have a certain body of knowledge so
let's say there's a certain tradition
that has an ecology of practices and a
certain view that supports that college
of practices
there could be so much stuff going on
there that they're not even aware of
explicitly that gets lost in translation
if you take it from their tradition
um so what i'm saying is when we mix and
matching it
i sense there's caution to even like
look at their views and then
take their views uh with the practices
um because there's so much going on
there that they might not even be
consciously aware of
yeah i'm curious if you have any
thoughts on that
uh i agree and i think um and and this
is also something i'll go into a bit is
like
views and how
you know they're colored by culture and
um they're limited you know there's
there
i like the term reality tunnel it's a
tunnel and it's it's a proper term
because a tunnel is limited
there's like dark space dark matter
around it
and there's no like one single
comprehensive view that's going to cover
everything it's just the nature of view
like you can share a view
and like you can kind of you know i can
try to embody the view that's presented
to me by someone
even if i try to follow it to a t it's a
different view the second i take it in
as my own because it's going to be
colored by my understanding of the
language
and my blind spots and all of that
so yeah i think i think it's helpful to
have a good sense of theory when
approaching views
as well as which they are
psychotechnologies
um but yeah to have a sense of their
that all views have their limitations
um and keep that in mind
well try to identify what they are
and keep that in mind as you're
exploring the world
through that view because people get
stuck in their view all the time and it
can be very problematic either for
themselves
or maybe not for themselves it might put
them in a very nice spot
and cause problems for other people
yeah all right um you want to keep going
with
some more questions uh yeah let's
stop after like oh it's already 3 30.
um i'll get into the thing now and
hopefully
you know if we have time at the end i'm
down to stick around for like a post
sense making session if other people are
um but i don't want to rush through the
presentation either
and there will be a little bit of time
for questions
my between my little spiels um but the
first thing i want to do is like
i'm feeling like a lot of energy in my
body i really wish i was in my kitchen
so that i could put my computer up on
something and like stand
uh because i like i just want to be
moving around so i'm going to take two
minutes
to like just do some somatic practice
and
you know even doing that right now i'm
like kind of breaking session protocol
i'm tweaking the
the session psychotech and i don't know
maybe peter isn't gonna like that idea
but you know that's
me practicing my sovereignty to some
extent and i'd invite anyone else to do
it as well if you want to like stretch
get into your body uh i'm gonna yeah i'm
gonna relax for a couple minutes
before i start talking because i'm like
alright is that cool peter all right two
minutes then
okay
i did a little bit of uh like shaky chi
gong i find that's helpful to break up
nervous energy belly breathing
kind of bringing like um
yeah like that kind of primal gut energy
like kind of
back into my body and like feeling that
centeredness
yeah okay so i'm gonna screen share
i'm gonna start with some like basic
stuff and if it feels like uh
like just so abstract it's not really
landing for you
i would say just like try to hold the
ideas because it might
present itself as like a good
scaffolding later
and if it's stuff that you're like super
super familiar with um and it's
redundant
uh i apologize but we're gonna get into
a little graphic visualization that i
drew up
okay everyone can see that right
great so
what what we're looking at is just
a a conceptual uh visualization
of what i was uh saying earlier i'm
gonna call
embodied metaphysics so we're like going
to touch
on basic philosophy um and then slowly
move that
into something more like experiential
that we can
relate to and ground a bit more
so the first thing to notice uh in this
picture
is the dual the dualistic aspect of
essence and emptiness
those terms come from um
taoism but if you were
talking to plato he would call it
um emptiness would be korra
which is like the receptacle of
experience
and essence would be like idea
there's another there's like a greek
word for it but it can be like idea or
form um
and to try to like ground these notions
a bit in something that might feel a bit
more intuitive
you can think of emptiness like
and this is like no metaphor really gets
to it
that's kind of the nature of of like um
trying to get non-dual about dualism but
emptiness can kind of be thought of as
like a canvas
um and
it's the blank space which allows for
form to arise you could say
very imperfect metaphor but um
and you can get this a little closer to
home by thinking about awareness itself
so we like having a sense of i whom who
is aware
and then all of this which i am aware of
but what is the nature of awareness
one way you could talk about that is
emptiness it's just like this
this empty whatever
in which form is appearing
so if like emptiness seems like super
esoteric and that's not the only way to
talk about emptiness but i think that's
a
a very helpful way to talk about it
and i kind of thought that that would be
like intuitive but i was talking to my
sister about this the other day and i
was like
you know how like you're just aware of
everything and she's like
well sometimes i'm aware i was like no
like i don't mean like
conscientious or something like that i
mean like you're just
aware there's there's awareness
happening
and she's kind of scratching her head
about it uh so
if you don't like kind of get this sense
of this field this like empty field of
awareness
it's something to like you know maybe
investigate a little
bit just it's not a thing
it can almost be felt or imputed or
something
so there's an emptiness to reality it's
the the
it's not an external emptiness i'm
talking about dark space i'm talking
about like the emptiness of
consciousness
um on the other side we have essence
and that's form um there's different
ways to think about that
as well you could think about it in a
very idealistic way
like i impute form onto everything
or you could talk about it in a more
energetic way which would be like a more
realistic materialist way like the
vibrational nature
of reality however you want to think
about it there's like a bajillion
ways to you know start slicing things up
but i think an intuitive way is
is energy you know like i just there's
the beingness
it's like active it's alive
um and
that's a good place to to start
because this idea of energy
and form and the idea of awareness and
emptiness
or plato's quora
are key concepts in a lot of psycho
technologies
you're working with your body you're
working with energy or you're working
with awareness you're trying to get you
know
even with stoicism you're getting the
view from above i think that really
points to
having a bigger space of emptiness
relaxing
back more into an empty space so that
you can see
more of the picture without getting like
caught up
in the ideas you know you're kind of
emptying yourself of your attachments to
things
um it's something that some people call
like
observer consciousness if you get like
really deep into it
but i'm already starting to like get
really uh
personal about it but abstractly we can
say emptiness in essence
so
as plato says there's like when you have
two a third is implied
and in the context of this visualization
we could say that the can you guys see
my my mouse cursor
yeah okay we could say that the third
is this line um
the the border between emptiness and
essence this is totally conceptual let's
keep this in mind
uh so we're it's all metaphor to a
certain extent but
we're getting somewhere with it so this
line
is the meeting place of emptiness and
essence it has properties of both
emptiness and essence
so it has a form like it even if it was
a straight line
that would be an integral aspect of what
it is like
a straight line or in this case like a
textured wavy line
it has an aspect of form to it
but it's also empty and that there's an
infinite quality to it so like this line
just
it's cut by our computer monitor but
idealistically it just goes on forever
right you can't
contain it so in that sense it's empty
of form so it's like
both at the same time
and that's the the third thing and you
can call it different things
um i'm not going to name it right now
because i i don't think it would be very
helpful but it's important to understand
this third that naturally arises from
the two or
i don't even want to say arises i think
it's just there you know they all three
colorize together
but because we need to conceptualize
things to
talk um what we're going to do is try to
find the most elegant way
to talk about uh this third and that i
would say is to make this
circle so this circle
is a conceptualization
of something so i'm i'm putting a box
around an arbitrary part of
the this dualistic reality and this is
what we might call
an idea or i would call it like a soul
although it kind of just it doesn't
matter too much what you want to call it
it's just like kind of the the the
fundamental
particles um of this metaphysics
and what yes so what we've done there is
we've taken like
the infinitude of emptiness and the
unknowableness of
essence and and the uh that kind of
um the heart of those two that third and
we're starting to like
bring concept into it
and once we do that we've got um
a few ways we can define this circle
like to bring it more into language
and here i'll start talking a little bit
about views
so in a more taoist view
you've got an energetic base for things
like in china you're more likely to see
people in the morning
out in the park doing some like tai chi
and qigong
before they're like sipping their coffee
or their tea and reading the newspaper
like we do in the west
and at an energetic level
you're working with transformation of
energy energy is just like
changing itself it's transforming from
this form to another
so if we're working in a kind of
bottom-up definition
what's going to be defining this concept
are the modes of transformation of
energy
and we have three that define this
circle so we have this bottom line
this middle line and this top line
where one form of energy gets
transformed to another gets transformed
to another gets transformed to another
so we have three
areas of transformation and you can
define
any i'd say anything and i recommend
reading force landry's book
and imminent metaphysics to like do you
want to really deeply grok
the triadic nature of reality
um but in this case so like with taoists
a lot of the the it's there's variance
and it's it's rich but
a lot of the thrust of taoist practice
is the transformation of essence
into emptiness through the soul
so you're looking at the transformation
from essence into what's called chi
or energy which is like your life energy
or your prana
or your kundalini or whatever you want
to call it and then you have the
transformation
of your personal energy into
what they call shen which is like your
soul
your spirit your kind of your selfness
and then you can transform that energy
into emptiness
now a top-down way of looking at things
what generally would be a more western
way
is to look at things not primarily from
the energy perspective but from the
emptiness percep
perspective which is as the receptacle
of forms so you're looking for forms
primarily
and to define this we have four forms
not
three we've got the form of essence or
the substance you might say of essence
we've got this half the bottom half the
top half
and then the emptiness itself
and a lot of what we're doing in the
west is doing a downward
motion we are looking to from a place of
emptiness from a place of the kind of
up here being a receptacle for form
generating forms manipulating forms
conceptualizing things
right um it's it's uh
including ourselves so like you know
we're we're
transforming ourselves we're
self-improving if
our project is a personal one um
and i would say that those forms line up
with
uh like wilbur's quadrants which i
haven't studied a lot of wilbur but
you've got a internal personal
and um someone correct me maybe peter
if i'm wrong here then there's like a
external personal
internal collective and an external
collective is that
language more or less right would you
guys say
yeah okay um and so a way to think about
that is
well the taoists name it too it's just
not like what they're trying to get at
so they they would say
uh and essence chi
shen emptiness and
what we're looking at is you know okay i
would say
ego up here awareness
it's the emptiness uh subconscious
down here and then um
the you could just say reality
or or pure form or the collective
unconscious if you'd like um
the the wholeness of form so to speak
so now we're going to start trying to
move this into
understanding this in a more embodied
way and how we make sense of it in terms
of psychotechnologies
um the
more popular thing to look at is over
here and these are the chakras
and these are if you take those four
quadrants conceptualize them
look at where they uh touch up against
each other
you've got your seven chakras you've got
the crown
chakra you've got your third eye you've
got your throat you've got your heart
you've got your solar plexus sacral
and root and those
can all be really i'd say well
understood
in terms of this fundamental metaphysics
if you understand if you got into it
which we're not going to
like what the ego is how does the ego
relate to awareness
knowingness how does the ego relate to
the subconscious the heart
it's not too hard and this is just my
personal view
to make sense of the chakras in that way
but what we're going to look at is this
which is
the um the tripart soul if i'm saying
that right
or the dantiens in taoism so we're going
to conceptualize these three
transformational centers and the very
common way to do that is to say the head
the heart and the gut or the hara
so this
basic schema is like everywhere i think
it's very intuitive
even if you haven't necessarily been
exposed to some philosophy that
mentions them uh but you'll find it like
i said
plato um traditional chinese
philosophy there's like a 17th century
irish druidic poem called the cauldrons
of poesie
and they named them the paul the
cauldron of warmth
the cauldron of movement the cauldron of
wisdom
uh there's the triads in kashmir
shaivism
and that's kind of more speaking to this
not so much embodied but you can bring
it into the embodied realm very quickly
um but what we kind of like commonly
would think of is like
head heart gut and there's a dif
there's a few different ways to make
sense of that and a lot of it's
intuitive like we all kind of
know what we mean when we say someone's
like really in their head
or like i'm feeling really centered in
my heart or this person really speaks
directly from their heart
or when you say someone's like really
got a good gut instinct about things or
they speak with
like uh from their guts you know um
but how can we make sense of that in a
way
that can be useful
there's the
the in the context of taoism you would
have the transformation of energy
as the main way you're making sense of
this
so for instance the gut there is like a
transformer
of the collective energy
into personal energy into your chi
so that could be anything from just
feeding yourself
um keeping your cellular body alive
or the more subtle energy bodies and
doing different practices
which result in higher amounts of qi
which if you're not very familiar with
qi you can talk about it different ways
but
most commonly it's described as like a
kind of felt
vibrational energy in the body
so then at the heart level you've got qi
being transformed into shen or spirit
and you can think about this as working
with
the energy you already have in yourself
and and making it personal in a way that
has
meaning so we have
um just our kind of like raw
life force and that's shaped
evolutionarily of course
and we can really talk about um how
you know evolution has made us you know
social beings
so to speak um but in a conceptual way
we can say it's us taking our life force
and learning and transforming it into
a person our actions
our feelings our our thoughts our
relations with others
um because we're not just like a
a web of vibrations right there's a
sense of like
the self as a concept like a self as a
unit as a whole
um personal me and you right
and so that's what the hearts doing it's
it's it's talking between
this self-hood that we know
and this more like energetic essential
self-hood
which simply is a more somatic self
which we can talk about again either
like in scientific terms the nervous
system all the brain all of that or more
subtle terms
energy systems kundalini and all that
and then you have the head and that's
taking
our personal sense of self um
and well
so if we say that this is emptiness is
kind of like awareness
or we could say that awareness is what
happens when you have a self
touching up against a fundamental
emptiness
you have the ability for a person to
then
have an experience right
awareness how does that happen
i'm everyone likes to think about that
or at least
a lot of people do the hard problem of
consciousness
um but we can talk about it in like a
more
easy way which is like you know just be
more aware
get a little more headspace right slow
down
take a a view from above
and there's so many practices which we
could name that do that
so that's the basics and
i want to stop now if peter if you see
any like really good
clarification type questions in the chat
where
um maybe something i've said isn't
really landing well
not so much i don't want to use too much
time to like kind of go down rabbit
holes right now
but if there's anything that feels like
really needs clarifying and what i've
gone over so far
i'm happy to answer some questions take
a quick
break for people to put some in as well
nothing's in the chest right now but we
can give it a few moments if you like
yeah i'll give it like 20 seconds or
something
it took a little longer than i wanted it
to but that's
uh my penchant for
rambling which i enjoy somewhere
uh robert has his hand raised
um okay
well feel free to unmute okay there we
go
so uh you were talking about view
and um there's also
the path and
the llamas talk about in and there seems
to be a place where
the view is something you have when you
don't know who you are
it's a story you tell yourself about our
experience or what we're trying what
we're trying to get to or
where we are and the path is that thing
we do
to get there but the llamas talk about
it and the zen people talk about
about there gets to be a place where the
path and the view are
the same there is no difference is that
there isn't anybody
having a view there's just a path
whatever it is it needs to happen
next that's pretty neat
yeah and and think
robert's a friend of mine uh we've had
like three hour long phone conversations
before
so i was like this question could last a
long time we're gonna find out
how big of a an area of conversation
we've just opened up
but yeah and i think that um
that difference between the path and the
view is a difference of bottom up and
top
down so for instance we can talk about a
view
but we can also ask where did a view
come from you know like
view is going to be transmitted to us
through language and
we have to start breaking down language
we have to start breaking down culture
we have to start getting into evolution
and break that down into energy and so
we can say
that like the path and the view are like
really
we can break them up and separate them
but we can also say that they're kind of
intertwined in a way that's they're
inseparable
um and a lot of like psychotechnologies
for instance
uh might be presented in this like very
discreet way
and you want to like get the view right
you want to get the the instructions
right
you have to ask like where where did
they come from like why did someone
start like
twisting their body in weird ways like
in yoga i believe
it's it's said that a lot of it was from
like imitating
animals i don't know um maybe it was
just an intuitive thing
it just started happening that wouldn't
come from a view
before there was a view about how to do
yoga properly or how to think about life
properly
there were people who were just maybe
playing
or experimenting or conditions impressed
themselves upon them such that
thoughts arose new ideas arose new
actions arose
and once they arise once you can start
to
they become possibly memes and can be
transmitted
um but yeah the path and the view are
just two conceptual ways of talking
about this one thing that's happening
but they're useful separations of how to
talk about it
yeah um so we've got 30 minutes left
i'm going to to tell a few stories about
my my journey
of psycho technologies now i'm going to
try to keep it down to
about 10 minutes which is gonna be
really hard because i like to tell
stories
um but we're gonna we're gonna do our
best
so
the technically the i would say the
first psycho technology i ever engaged
in
was accidental it would have been when i
was 19
just out of high school i had
an hour and 45 minute bus ride
each way to my job
and uh i'm 35 now so this was you know
16 17 years ago 16 years ago
so i didn't have an iphone i wasn't
bringing books or game boys or anything
like that i was just sitting there
and well if i could i would just fall
asleep
which is kind of its own psycho
technology to try to sleep on a public
bus
but a useful one actually and i'll i'll
mention this um
i would try to sleep on the bus but i
didn't want to miss my stop
and so i would try to get into this like
half asleep
state of mind where i was relaxed as
possible but i still had like a little
antenna up
that would like listen for cues and like
hear the bus stops being named and stuff
like that
i was trying to get as relaxed as i
could without falling asleep
and little did i know that that's like a
big element of a lot of meditations
is getting this very relaxed place
um so i was doing that
um i was also running to catch the bus
in the mornings
like i had to sprint there because i'm
you know waking up super late
so i'm starting my day off with like
exercise which you can't like
usually get me to exercise unless it's
something fun like playing
tennis or going hiking but as it were i
was starting each day with like a sprint
for like 10 minutes and then this like
deep relaxation
and then i'd have the rest of my uh my
drive to work and then on my way back
just to
to think about things and so i was
practicing
i don't know what the good like um
like socratic terminology would be for
this or
but basically having a deep inner
dialogue
and thinking things over very deeply i
was moved to
consider all of my discontents with my
parents
and break them down so deeply that i
could present an argument
about why they were wrong that was like
totally impenetrable
and i was able to like imagine that my
parents were
quite a bit more intelligent than they
were so i was having to refine my
my arguments deeper and deeper and
really break things down
into their essence and i was touching
upon
a lot of like basic philosophical
notions
contemplative spiritual notions about
suffering
about ignorance and blind spots and and
all of this stuff
and holding making space for that every
day looking at it from different angles
and over the course of a month of this
practice
one day it just like kind of flipped
around on me
and i was like okay if i'm going to be
really true to what i'm saying here it
doesn't make sense to hold any
resentment towards my parents
and where it does make sense to put that
energy is upon myself like to live by
these principles which
i've investigated deeply and feel very
alive for me
and it was really like and uh
almost like a physical transformation
happened where suddenly
like the energy started flowing
differently and it felt like my chest
like opened up
a bit and like just kind of like water
was like pouring out of it
i felt very empowered i felt um
happy peaceful and
spent the rest of my bus trips you know
thinking further
deepening into that um
and that led to great experiences like
learning to like pass on
negative thoughts
i would start to feel them arising which
like unformed just like a habit of
wanting to like complain about
and before it would turn into a
thought i would like let go
and it would just turn into gratitude i
was like very happy to be alive
and i felt very connected to other
people i could sense
within everyone else this like same
basic desire to want to be happy and
so it was great i was like you know very
happy
um for for quite a while and then i got
into a relationship
and it all went like just like a sinking
ship
it just went away because trying to
embody that
in a relationship i had no no context
for doing it i suppressed a lot of my
intuitions
um in service of trying to keep the
relationship going
like holding my tongue about this or
that where i wanted to like
you know have conversations about stuff
that would come up for me
and so from there i would say to
maybe five years ago like understanding
myself at an emotional level has been
my work and been in a lot of
relationships
i made art for a long time wrote a lot
of songs
write poetry and just was trying to
understand
my feelings and and
increasing my capacity to embody those
feelings understanding where they're
coming from
eventually got into some psychotherapy
and you know tracing things down and all
that
but didn't really do any formal
meditation practices
uh except right after i broke up
in that relationship um i tried to
meditate
i read a book called magic and mysticism
in tibet by alexander david neal
and that turned me on to the idea of
like spirituality
i didn't know what the i was doing
but i was like all right it's something
about breathing and exhales are longer
than the outhail
um the inhale so i went in my closet
every day and it would just sit there
and try to like manipulate my breath
which didn't do much i just get
distracted by like hypnagogic colors and
stuff
and then one day i'm meditating and i
just start to feel this like little
tightness in the center of my chest and
it starts to like expand
and it's just this like arid tight
feeling of like my chest my heart
turning into a desert
it's very painful i'm like this sucks
what the so i just stopped
meditating because i was like i don't
know what i'm doing i'm gonna like
screw myself up so i didn't really
meditate
um for i'd say about
10 years after that again i was just
doing like art which is
own psycho technology for sure
um but don't have time to talk about all
of that
uh as i was getting more into psychology
jungian spirituality um
i decided to start trying to meditate
again
but it would bring up um a lot of
anxiety
um i noticed that on my exhales there
was just this
crazy anxious feeling about wanting to
get my next inhale
in it's very uncomfortable it sucked so
i tried it a while and then just gave up
and then i went to um
india with a girlfriend and while we
were there
i was like let's let's go to like a
proper meditation retreat center and try
that out and she was down
and we did a 10-day session and then she
took off to like do some yoga and
rishikesh and i was like i like this so
i stayed for another 10-day session and
then did another two-day session after
that
and had a deep dive into meditative
practice like
tibetan buddhist tradition and i like
you know
figured out like this much of how to
meditate like nothing but it was
a lot more than zero so
i i got back and let me like use that
part of the narrative to um
talk about psychotechnologies in the
context of
uh setting um
meditating when you're like in a
beautiful retreat center surrounded by
all this like beautiful buddhist
art and really relaxed cool
people and like monkeys and and
everyone's quiet
there's like a silent retreat it makes
it a lot easier
to learn to meditate um
so right away you can see the importance
of like
setting in and approaching a psycho
technology
you can try it in your bedroom and have
no success whatsoever
even if you have all the you know really
good instructions
just because of the setting and the
amount of time you have to dedicate
it to it um so it's like a really
complex thing to really consider
all the variables in what constitutes a
psychotechnology
it's not limited to just what's going on
in your head or in your body
um so anyways i get back to the united
states
um i'm in texas
and to record an album and i
start trying to continue my meditation
practice and
i'm getting like floods of overwhelming
emotion
um i don't know what it is i don't know
what it means where it's coming from
it just feels like a sea of feelings
that i might drown in
and so i was like i don't want to go too
much deeper with this practice right now
i instinctively felt like i needed to do
a physical practice and i'd heard about
qigong
so i just got on youtube and started
doing some qigong
really basic primer uh series of
movements
and that was amazing it was like i wish
someone had been
showing me qigong when i was like 10
years old and freaking out and
i bet that would have helped a lot with
add as a kid for instance
to be able to like do some somatic
practices between classes to settle my
body
um but anyways so i started doing qigong
every day
and it was wonderful and definitely
helped me to have a higher capacity
for holding emotion but in addition to
that i started going to psychotherapy
and you know trying i wanted to
understand where all this emotion was
coming from
figured i need some help and that was a
great both of those were great
complementary practices um to my
meditation practice
so there we're like talking more about
you know maybe
uh psychotech stacking or i heard it
phrased a different way recently
um but yeah having having different
things in your life different practices
which
um all are all informing you in such a
way that you can practice
the rest of the practice as well kind of
synergy
of practices in your life um
from there where are we at 409
then oh here's a little tidbit
i took the train from texas from austin
to l.a
and i i decided to eat three weed
cookies
which is so stupid but like i was like
you know
kind of had this ego about wanting to
like push myself
and see like oh yeah i could handle that
i had a terrible time
it's really bad when you're like so high
that wanting to move your hand has a
three second delay before your hand
actually moves
it's very freaky um i think i walked
back and down the full set of the train
cars like five times looking for my seat
after i went to pee
and it was really no good once i decided
the train was
moving too fast it just
made me pretty miserable um
so yeah already like it's like
i had to learn in a hard-headed way as i
often do
about how to be careful with
psychotechnologies including
psychedelics
um but yeah be be careful especially
when
mixing psychedelics with well with
yourself
to begin with but with any other
meditation practice because it's really
hard to predict
what's going to happen um psychedelics
works so deeply
that you know i would say if you're
going to do it at all start with like
mini micro doses and titrate your way
into more just like just the tiniest bit
because it's it's really important to be
careful with those
anyway so now i'm in la and
um i'm doing a few things that are new
all at once
i take this course called finders course
it's put together by this guy jeffrey
martin and you can watch an interview
with him
on daniel schmoktenberger's podcast
i forget what it's called the podcast
but
it's with i think it's with his neuro
hacker on his website there
and this course is um
designed by someone who was researching
enlightened states of consciousness and
um trying to understand in a really
practical way how you alter your
consciousness
towards whatever enlightenment or
whatever you want to call it
um rather than and kind of disregarding
views
and looking at the path as robert put it
like i don't care what your philosophy
is
you know yours that you don't have a
cell for this or that or blah blah blah
he was wanted to like very um
with a high level of resolution and a
large sample base
like i think like 2 000 people get a
sense of like what practices
work to to shift people's consciousness
and he came up with i think like 12
like gold standard practices which seem
to work for people
so in this course you you go through all
of them
and you the idea is that you try to find
the one that like resonates with you
most
um because another thing he found in his
research was that
you can do a practice for like ever like
you could be practicing zazen for
decades 30 years and make some progress
but
not nearly the progress that you want to
be making
or which is promised to you and someone
doing this will then switch to a new
practice
and get results very quickly so that
brings us this notion of method matching
uh the idea that like practices are not
just
like hammers and nails um
everyone's different everyone's got
their own psychological makeup their own
energetic propensities and postures
and different technologies are going to
work well for different people
depending on who you are and and what
you want out of it too
so that kind of opened my mind to the
idea of of
you know not getting stuck on any one
technology for too long
and in addition to doing that course i
was doing a holotropic breath work class
and the the instructor there
i didn't know this because it was my
first introduction to breath work but he
was
bringing in other practices with breath
work he was very against mixing it with
psychedelics
um again and i thought like a kind of
close-minded way but i
i think it's very intense to do that and
i would never recommend it to people
but i don't think you need to make a
rule around it
but he would do things like in between
uh
breathing uh sets laughter meditations
or um i don't know what these things
were called at the time
uh but things such as progressive
relaxation
um which is i think works really well
with holotropic breath work and i do
that regularly whenever i do breath work
and then there's um the music he was
playing for instance
uh trying to do breath work in a quiet
room versus doing it in a room where
there's
um really relaxing music is
a big difference you know as like i said
before
art making art but also art itself is a
powerful psychotechnology and something
to consider
um and we did some like body relaxation
so anyways you know we had all these
different things and then i was also
doing like high intensity interval
training
a bit of yoga and i was noticing
how all these different things the
meditation course i was doing
the breath work and more just like phys
qi gong and yoga and um high intensity
interval training
we're all informing each other in
interesting ways i guess i was doing
like non-dualistic practices of
awareness
um my the experiences i was having in
breath work were starting to change
where i was like
getting to those same places but faster
and more deeply
um and maybe the first instance of me
kind of creating my own bespoke
psychotech you might say
was one day where i had this thought pop
into my head
which is what do my thoughts feel like
it's like that's an interesting question
i didn't really know what to do with it
but that evening i'm doing my breath
work and
while we're relaxing at the end of the
session
i like the question pops back into my
mind what do my thoughts
feel like and i
i didn't i didn't know how to answer
that with more thoughts that didn't make
much sense
so i just started paying attention to
the aesthetic
quality of my thoughts like how are they
showing up in relation to the rest of my
experience
so i was already deeply embodied from
the breath work which
worked really well for me as far as
relaxing me letting me get into my
system
and uh feel like my internal energy and
being grounded in that um i think helped
me to observe
my my thoughts in a way where i wasn't
like caught up in them so much
i was kind of anchored a bit more so
then when i was
sitting there with this this question
and i was you know kind of
what i like i said aesthetically aware
of my thoughts rather than engaging with
the meaning of my thoughts
after some time all of a sudden my
thoughts just stopped
they're just like gone i was like what
and
that lasted maybe 20 seconds before i
got so excited i like stood up
in the class and was
like thinking about it like that's crazy
um and it was like immediately trying to
like you know make sense of it and all
that kind of thing
um so so there was an instance where
there's two
psycho technologies i was practicing and
all the other ones that the instructor
would mix in
that deeply informed each other like the
groundedness and embodiment
of the breath work gave me um a capacity
for
observing my thoughts in a
non-interfering way
which i'd never done before and part of
it was something that just came out of
nowhere right
like that idea to to ask myself what do
my thoughts feel like
no one ever told that to me it's just a
thought that popped up in my head and i
went with it
so i made my own my own tech there
um we got 12 more minutes
i i think i'm going to pivot now to
some some like catchy
easy ways to to think about all this
stuff i've just been talking about
uh like little questions you can ask
yourself when thinking about
psychotechnologies
you know that might be helpful so
the first i would say well first of all
peter are there any like super good
questions that are worth
talking about right now
um
i don't know uh you touched on a lot of
them so maybe if something is alive for
someone maybe you can copy and paste
your question or
write a new one i'd say that's your one
question because i do want to get some
more stuff in before the 90 minutes is
over and then again we have
i'm happy to stick around afterwards to
field some more q a is that possible
peter
yeah we have an event at uh six eastern
time so
probably should close up at that and
popcorn style anyone can just unmute
themselves so i think we have high
discerning people here
okay i'll give everyone a chance real
quick if someone
really wants to ask something
a christian wants me to read this one uh
how do you deal with rumination or the
possibility of rumination
oh like just mental rumination while
you're like trying to focus on your
practice like getting caught up
in thoughts like
seems yes okay um
for me the the thing i just talked about
the feeling my thoughts was the first
thing that really helped me with that
um and that practice is i'll like
explain it a little bit but it's it's
something very intuitive
which is to try to get an aesthetic
relationship
to the process of thinking so normally
when we think about our thoughts we're
trying to you know relate them to other
thoughts basically like what do i mean
by this thought
or you're just kind of following it down
like a narrative
trail right um
when it comes to um and you know people
will say like in your meditation just
let
thoughts come and go and i never had
much luck with that
uh i think the the deeply ingrained
habit of following my thoughts was
was a big part of my my character
so to um and there's different ways to
deal with this
um and so i'm just really presenting one
way
um but this this practice was a way
where i was
changing my um
my mode of awareness from this very
mental
awareness of the web of meaning in the
mind
to a slightly more embodied mode of
awareness which is aesthetic
and if you don't have a lot of access to
that now i would say like a good thing
to do would be to practice
photography or or arts right um
do something where all of your attention
is not about the meaning of what you're
looking at but like
the form the colors the textures
the the composition the balances um
it's a more artful way to look at things
and i found that by switching into that
artful mode
rather than my meaning making mode i was
able to let
rumination just kind of recede into the
background
or you know sometimes it doesn't go so
well and you're just kind of like
switching back and forth between
little spurts of getting caught in your
thoughts and then what do my thoughts
feel like and then
get remember to get grounded in your
body so and that's the other thing i'd
say with rumination
is to have a solid foundation in your
body
is really really really helpful but
that's a huge project
because the body is your storehouse of
experiences
and there's all sorts of in there
um the
the vipassana style like gawanka style
body scanning meditation
for me was insanely difficult
uh when i first started doing it first
of all rumination was like just a killer
and i was just in my thoughts constantly
and and feeling bad about that
um like you know god i can't do
this and creating frustration or shame
which was just creating more thoughts it
was gnarly
um but i stuck with it and i'll use this
story actually
to seg into some of the principles
so when i was doing
um goenka style body scanning
i starting to get these really weird
tensions in my head it felt not like a
headache but more like someone had stuck
a magnet in my head
and like the field of energy was like
getting distorted it just it felt wrong
it didn't feel good it wasn't painful
but i was like this is this is a problem
and there was nothing in the instruction
in the course that addressed that
and i wasn't getting helpful feedback
from the people who run the course
but i went online i like went to like
reddit and some forums and and just
tried to
you know wisely google my way into an
answer
that would address this phenomena and i
found two things
uh one person was saying it's good to
get into your heart more before you
start doing your body scanning
i thought okay that sounds like a good
idea and then another person said hey
it's really good to center in your gut
before you start doing body scanning
and i thought okay that sounds like a
good idea so
i bespoked a little psychotec where
i would when i started my practice i
would take
three breaths focusing on my hara area
the gut
and i would think about relaxation i
would just be like you know peacefulness
groundedness
relaxed safe all of this
and then i would take three breaths
where i was focusing on my heart and i
would think like you know
i wouldn't think words so much but more
just like a feeling of like positivity
um connection like a it's like a green
light like thumbs up like yeah
and then after three breaths there i
would take three breaths
and just move into my awareness of my
body sensations
and do scanning for three breaths and
this worked really well for me
and it helped me to do the body scans
without
getting so triggered because i had a lot
of
uh somatic trauma basically and these
augmenting it with these relaxing and
heart opening exercises
allowed me to do the practice in a way
that was manageable
and it led to some pretty deep
experiences too
but it didn't necessarily cure
all those anxieties there were some like
purges of you know mental
um but in general it was just like a way
to make the practice work
but that's that's good too um
sometimes you have to like just get what
you can afford
and so you might not be able to like
fully address
your traumas that are showing up in your
meditation practice
but you might be able to do something
that helps you meditate through them or
you know ease them just while you're
meditating and then that meditation
might like give you enough clarity that
you can change your
life situation a bit so that you can
open up some space for
uh going to therapy or or whatever you
might do to help address
those deeper traumas um
so with the five minutes i have left the
four minutes i'm gonna
try to cram in some some things really
quickly
one is this this back to the the
metaphysics the head the heart and the
gut
it can be helpful to think about
practices um
in this framework um
one you can think about what energy
center does a practice
draw upon so like is it primarily like a
physical
um or energetic gut oriented practice
um is it an emotional practice where
you're interfacing with your heart
or is it a mental practice something
more view oriented
or contemplative or pure awareness type
of practice
and then the other question is like what
is the purpose of the practice
what is it trying to do which energy
center is it working on
so for instance um
you could have a practice like
contemplative prayer right you are
you choose a word it's like a monster
type of thing
you usually choose like a religiously
oriented word
that feels good to you when i did it i
would use the word hallelujah
and you you choose a word that naturally
elicits
emotion in you right which you might not
be able to find one in which case you
need to
go to a whole nother technology to start
opening up your heart and getting your
emotions flowing
but if you can find a word that like
makes you feel something
you use that as a contemplative anchor
and it's called centering prayer because
what it does is it centers your mind
can help with the rumination so you're
centering into this heart feeling
so it's a heart oriented it's like
coming from the heart but what you're
doing is having an effect on your mind
you're you're learning to still your
mind and focus it and bring greater
clarity
um and awareness so that would be like
in the taoist system
i would say um moving shen
from shen to emptiness right or
centeredness which is kind of
they go hand in hand in some ways uh and
then another thing might be like
um
well in taoism there they have like a
whole system like if you want to do
something there's like a procedure for
it
i could name so many um but let's like
look at a top-down one like
uh well i'm not gonna give any more
examples right now
i'm gonna say one other thing in the
last minute and a half
which is set and setting which we
already went over a bit well we went
over setting
um how important setting is your
environment
set is mindset which is like you know
what's going on internally
so it's the the situation that you find
yourself within
and the situation which you find within
yourself and those are both
going to strongly affect the practice
itself including your motivations for
doing it if you're dealing with traumas
depressions
your expectations um all that stuff
like don't do acid when you're 19 and
severely depressed and anxious because
you might have like a month-long bad
trip
just saying it might happen but i want
to add two more things to that
which is sit and
sitting so sit would be
your body and what are you doing with
your body
while you're meditating are you sitting
down is your body relaxed
are you holding tension are you laying
down are you walking are you standing
all of these things are things to think
about um
are you on a comfortable surface are you
doing something like crazy like
uh you know lotus position because
that's what you're supposed to do but
like you're so distracted by the
discomfort
that you can't focus on the meditation
so the somatic elements
how is my body right now what am i doing
with my body do i need to try walking
while i meditate that's something to
consider
and then the last thing would be sitting
which is who's
sitting with you who is are you doing it
by yourself
might it be useful to work with a group
are you doing it with someone who is
inhibiting your practice because you
don't want to be out of alignment with
what they're doing like maybe an
instructor or a guru or someone
so finding other people or finding the
alone space that you need
or the people that you just have in your
head you know like who's sitting
with you in an imaginary way who's like
watching you meditate and judging your
practice
uh these are all things to consider and
that's
that's all the time i have friends so
thanks a lot for this peter i hope i
managed to uh
get a lot in without you know it being
too dense i was pretty non-stop the
whole time
um and yeah i'm happy to stick around
for some q a
afterwards cool
uh so thank you christian for uh coming
today sharing your thoughts on bespoke
cycle technology
after i press stop record i have to
bounce but you guys can stay in this
room until
about 30 minutes there's always a
discord too you can hop on and continue
the conversation
and i'm just going to plug a few events
so the one we have at 6 pm eastern time
glass b game psycho technology here at
the stoa
uh where you kind of create uh and sense
make reality on the spot
and uh one tomorrow another kind of
psychotech method
called existential kink with carolyn
eddie elliott um maybe gray's gonna be
hosting that one
that's at 5 30 p.m eastern time and um
yeah you can read the description it's
kind of cool it's kinky
um so uh that being said go to store
patreon account
stop stack all that good stuff and uh i
will um
play some music so we want a bio break
and then i'll take christian back in